## **Emily Wall**

My research involves decision making using data visualization and visual analytics. I develop computational strategies to characterize human limitations in decision making (e.g., cognitive bias) and design interventions to promote reflective data analysis and decision making processes.

I will be joining the Department of Computer Science at Emory University as an Assistant Professor in Fall 2021. I am currently completing a Postdoc at Northwestern University with Jessica Hullman and Steve Franconeri (Summer 2020 - Summer 2021). I completed my Ph.D. in Computer Science at Georgia Tech in 2020.

PDF OF CV

## **Appointments**

2021- Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science

**Emory University** 

2020-2021 Postdoctoral Researcher

Department of Computer Science

Northwestern University

## **Education**

2020 Ph.D. in Computer Science

Georgia Institute of Technology

Thesis: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

Committee: Alex Endert, John Stasko, Polo Chau, Brian Fisher, Wenwen Dou

2015 B.S. in Computer Science & Mathematics

University of Georgia summa cum laude

## **Honors & Awards**

2019	GVU Foley Scholar, Recipient, Georgia Institute of Technology
2019	D.E. Shaw Exploration Fellowship, Recipient
2019	Siemens FutureMaker Fellowship, Recipient
2018	GVU Foley Scholar, Finalist, Georgia Institute of Technology
2017	Graduate Student Symposium, Participant, AT&T Labs

2017	Doctoral Colloquium, Participant, IEEE VIS
2017-2020	Graduate Fellowship for STEM Diversity (GFSD), Recipient
2017	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program, Honorable Mention
2017	Department of Defense SMART Fellowship, Recipient (Declined)
2015-2019	President's Fellowship, Recipient, Georgia Institute of Technology
2015	CURO Symposium Best Paper Award, University of Georgia
2014	CURO Research Assistantship, University of Georgia
2014	Hahn Family Scholarship for Computer Science, Recipient, University of Georgia
2013	Hollingsworth Award for Excellence in Mathematics, Recipient, University of Georgia
2012-2015	Zell Miller Scholarship, Recipient, University of Georgia

### **Publications**

#### **Journal Articles**

#### A Heuristic Approach to Value-Driven Evaluation of Visualizations

E. Wall, M. Agnihotri, L. Matzen, K. Divis, M. Haass, A. Endert, and J. Stasko IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. InfoVis'18), 2019.

PDF | □ Talk | ⊕ Website | ▶ Video FF

#### Podium: Ranking Data Using Mixed-Initiative Visual Analytics

E. Wall, S. Das, R. Chawla, B. Kalidindi, E. Brown, and A. Endert IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. VAST'17), 2018.

#### AxiSketcher: Interactive Nonlinear Axis Mapping of Visualizations through User Drawings

B.C. Kwon, H. Kim, *E. Wall*, J. Choo, H. Park, and A. Endert

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. VAST'16), 2017.

► PDF | Video

#### **Conference Proceedings**

#### Toward a Design Space for Mitigating Cognitive Bias in Vis

E. Wall, J. Stasko, and A. Endert

*IEEE Information Visualization (VIS) Short Papers*, 2019.

🖺 PDF | 🖿 Supplemental | 🖽 Talk | ▶ Video FF

#### A Markov Model of Users' Interactive Behavior in Scatterplots

E. Wall, A. Arcalgud, K. Gupta, and A. Jo

IEEE Information Visualization (VIS) Short Papers, 2019.

PDF | ⊞ Talk | ▶ Video FF

#### A Formative Study of Interactive Bias Metrics in Visual Analytics Using Anchoring Bias

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, and A. Endert

*Proceedings of the 17th IFIP TC 13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (INTERACT'19)*, 2019.

PDF | ► Video

## Using Expert Patterns in Assisted Interactive Machine Learning: A Study in Machine Teaching

E. Wall, S. Ghorashi, and G. Ramos

*Proceedings of the 17th IFIP TC 13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (INTERACT'19)*, 2019.

PDF | ▶ Video

## Warning, Bias May Occur: A Proposed Approach to Detecting Cognitive Bias in Interactive Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, L. Franklin, and A. Endert IEEE Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST), 2017.

PDF | ⊞ Talk | ▶ Video | ▶ Video FF

#### Supporting Team-First Visual Analytics through Group Activity Representations

S.K. Badam, Z. Zeng, *E. Wall*, A. Endert, and N. Elmqvist *Graphics Interface*, 2017.

 PDF | ▶ Video

### **Workshop Papers**

#### Four Perspectives on Human Bias in Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, K. Cook, and A. Endert

DECISIVe: Workshop on Dealing with Cognitive Biases in Visualizations (at InfoVis'17), 2017.

₽DF

#### **Book Chapters**

#### Four Perspectives on Human Bias in Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, K. Cook, and A. Endert

Cognitive Biases in Visualizations, Ed. G. Ellis, Springer, 2018, Chapter 3, pp. 29-42.

**■** Book | **■** Chapter

#### **Theses**

#### **Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics**

Emily Wall

Georgia Tech, School of Interactive Computing Ph.D. Thesis. April 2020.

₽DF

## **Professional Experience**

2015-2020 Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Graduate Research Assistant Advised by Dr. Alex Endert

Thesis: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

Summer Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, Richland, WA

<sup>2016</sup> Intern, Visual Analytics Group

Mentored by Lyndsey Franklin and Kris Cook

Developed heuristics to characterize bias in real-time from user interaction

sequences

2013-2015 **Jet Propulsion Laboratory**, Pasadena, CA

Intern, Systems Engineering Group

Advised by Marc Sarrel

Used SysML and principles of Model-Based Systems Engineering to visualize

network flows for Lockheed Martin's Orion capsule

Fall 2014 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Don Potter

Developed neural network to predict solar radiation in Georgia; funded by the

Georgia Power Advanced Solar Initiative

Fall 2013 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Liming Cai

Used sequence alignment techniques to determine coevolution of species with a

common ancestor

Spring 2013 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant Advised by Dr. Prashant Doshi

Created simulation and programmable interface for Parrot A.R. Drone

quadcopters to serve as a testbed for autonomous decision making with UAVs

## **Grants & Funding**

2019-2020 Toward Mitigating Cognitive Bias for Data-Driven Decision Making with Visual

Analytics

Siemens FutureMaker Fellowship

Co-PIs: Dr. Alex Endert Funded: \$101,435

2019 Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

GVU Foley Scholar
Co-Pls: Dr. Alex Endert
Funded: \$5,000

<sup>2017-2020</sup> Toward Mitigating Cognitive Bias for Data-Driven Decision-Making With Visual

#### **Analytics**

Graduate Fellowship for STEM Diversity (GFSD)

Co-Pls: Dr. Alex Endert

Funded: \$20,000 / year for 3 years

2014 Predicting Solar Radiation in Georgia

CURO Research Assistantship

Co-Pls: <u>Dr. Don Potter</u> Funded: \$1,000

## **Teaching**

### **Teaching Assistant**

Spring 2019	Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460) (133 students) Georgia Institute of Technology
Fall 2017	Information Visualization (CS 7450) (74 students) Georgia Institute of Technology
Fall 2013	Introduction to Computing and Programming (CSCI 1301) University of Georgia
Fall 2012	Introduction to Computing and Programming (CSCI 1301) University of Georgia

#### **Guest Lectures**

Feb 2019	Introduction to Javascript Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460), Georgia Institute of Technology
Dec 2017	Cognition in Visualization Information Visualization (CS 7450), Georgia Institute of Technology
Nov 2017	<b>Visual Analytics</b> Information Visualization (CS 7450), Georgia Institute of Technology
Jun 2017	Visualization Design: Do's and Don'ts Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460), Georgia Institute of Technology

## **Presentations**

#### **Invited Talks**

#### As We Are: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

> May 2020. CMU & AFRL, Center for Excellence on Human-Machine Teaming. Virtual Brown Bag.

- > May 2020. Siemens. Virtual Brown Bag.
- > March 2020. Cornell University, Info Science Colloquium. Ithaca, NY. ݮ Abstract
- > February 2020. University of Washington, Allen School Colloquium. Seattle, WA. 🔄 Watch
- > February 2020. Emory University. Atlanta, GA. 🗗 Abstract
- > February 2020. New York University. New York, NY. 🛂 Abstract
- > February 2020. University of Wisconsin. Madison, WI.

#### Left, Right, and Gender: Mitigating Implicit Human Bias in Visual Analytics

> January 2020. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Brown Bag. Atlanta, GA. 🛂 Watch

#### The Interactive Analytics Library: Treating Interaction as Data

> May 2017. Pacific Northwest National Laboratory. Richland, WA.

#### **Posters and Demonstrations**

## Warning, Bias May Occur: Detecting and Mitigating Cognitive Bias in Visual Analytics (Poster & Demo)

- > October 2019. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > June 2019. Summer Institute on Bounded Rationality. Berlin, Germany.
- > April 2019. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

# Warning, Bias May Occur: A Proposed Approach to Detecting Cognitive Bias in Interactive Visual Analytics (Demo)

- > April 2018. CRA-W Grad Cohort. San Francisco, CA.
- > April 2018. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2017. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

#### Podium: Ranking Data Using Mixed-Initiative Visual Analytics (Poster & Demo)

- > April 2018. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2017. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2018. CRA-W Grad Cohort. San Diego, CA.
- > April 2016. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

## **Mentoring**

2020	Jamal Paden, B.S. Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of
	2020
	Conducted usability testing for bias mitigation interventions
2017-2018	<b>Yingxiao Ouyang</b> , M.S. HCI, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2019 Conducted usability testing and prototyping for bias mitigation interventions
2017	Qiaochu Mu, M.S. HCI, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2018 Conducted usability testing and prototyping for bias mitigation interventions
2016-2017	<b>Bharath Kalidindi</b> , B.S. Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2018  Developed system for ranking data from user interaction

#### Service

#### 2020 Organizer

Trust and Expertise in Visual Analytics (TREX) Workshop at IEEE VIS

#### Program Committee Member

IEEE VIS Short Papers, 2020

VISxAl Workshop at IEEE VIS, 2019 CHI Late Breaking Work, 2018

#### Reviewer

IEEE VIS: 2020, 2019, 2018, 2017

CHI: 2020, 2019, 2018

EuroVis: 2020 TVCG: 2018

International Journal of Human-Computer Studies: 2019

KDD IDEA: 2017 VAST Challenge: 2016

2017 Panelist

Advancing Visualization Inclusion and Diversity (AVID) Workshop at IEEE VIS

2018-2020 Graduate Student Council Chair, School of Interactive Computing

Representative of graduate students in the School of Interactive Computing

2017-2018 Graduate Student Council Travel Committee

Responsible for reviewing and awarding travel grants to graduate student applicants in the College of Computing

## **Selected Media**

Nov 2019 A Reflection on VIS2019: Or, How Doomed Are We? Medium Blog Post,

Multiple Views on Visualization Research Explained.

by Michael Correll

Nov 2019 Highlights from IEEE VIS 2019, Uncharted Software Blog. ■ Read

by Rosa Romero-Gomez

May 2019 Battling Bias. Ep. 3, Tech Unbound Podcast. • Listen

with Josh Preston

## **Other Professional Activities**

Oct 2019 NextProf Nexus Workshop

Atlanta, GA

Jun 2019 Summer Institute on Bounded Rationality

Berlin, Germany

Apr 2018 CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop

San Francisco, CA

Oct 2016 Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing

Houston, TX

Apr 2016 CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop

San Diego, CA